[Music]
you know that if a statement a implies
statement
B not B implies statement not b not
a huh yeah there those Al equivalent you
know this this is called sometimes the
Contra positive of this
statement are you all familiar with this
okay if you think this is easy let's
consider the following
example if
Shema is not angry at
Tadashi then Tadashi does not
work okay it's only when Shima is angry
at Tadashi that Tadashi says okay okay I
come out of bed and I work let's accept
this which is more this true
anyway it should be equivalent to say if
Tadashi works then sha becomes angry
at that doesn't sound
equivalent what happened an exercise
[Music]
okay curious
logic so this ex this uh theorem also
shows that the leftest number being non
zero sorry leest number being
zero let's do it like this not equal to
minus plus or minus
one so it can be two 3 Z and so on but
it's not plus or minus one um means
that um f is not deformable to a
constant
man the way professionals talk about it
is that leest number is an obstruction
to deformability to a con Conant it
obstructs your some of your
projects for this in this connection you
should look at the example number
six the case when n is not equal to zero
and you'll see what I mean okay let's
press
on the coral that we Harvest do you
remember this word coral lar cor that we
Harvest is super
famous yesterday we encounter the Jordan
curve theorem and it's generalization to
any Dimension and although you all said
in the that you have never heard of it
30 seconds later Thea says oh I have
heard of it and everyone has heard of it
too that was very strange so now I'd
like to ask you has anybody in the
room heard of the brow fixed Fone
the yes ah somebody says yes who said
yes oh tabuka has heard of
everything anybody else heard of brow
fix
point please note that this is brow a
Dutch name and it's pronounced maybe can
help how do you pronounce this in
Africans R okay I I think I have some
reason to believe that
it's in Dutch it would be the
same approximate okay so the
mathematicians around the world maybe
with the exception of Dutch people he's
he was a Dutch person called him BR but
maybe b anyway fix Point here
however you pronounce name and this is a
super famous theorem and I'll tell you
in a number of applications examples
later tomorrow why Super Famous it's
very very useful you'll be amazed to
what variety of practical problems in
applied sciences you can apply this
theorem for the time being
statement is that every continuous map
F from you remember this
notation is the mble it is not this
spherical but it's a solid stuff M
dimensional b m dimensional B yeah has a
fixed
point in particular if you have a dis
any mapping of the dis into itself which
is continuous must have a fixed Point
must leave some point fixed any mapping
from the interv itself must leave a
fixed point and so on and so
on okay I said continuous map in order
to
emphasize actually all the maps that we
have been considering are continuous I
thought that you assume this so we
didn't state it every time everything
that we do is continuous anyway but here
I emphasized
continuity for no reason but psychology
okay
the simplest example is this what does
the onedimensional ball look like one
ball interal
so the map from 1D to
1d looks like
this and I claim that you must cross the
Diagon why is this because you see the
graph must go from this side to this
side and diagonal is way waiting there
so you must cross it you must say oh
what if I start from here and then go
there I don't seem to have cross the
diag no no no you are at the diagonal at
the
origin so it's important to include both
end points otherwise you might miss the
fixed point but as long as the interval
is closed closed in the sense of General
topology it includes the end points he
has all the boundary points then he has
a fixed Point similarly it's important
in this that b m was defined to be a
closed
ball so B of M can be replaced
by by any
set homeomorphic to the B it can be a
square it can be a triangle it can be
anything it can be some strange shape
provided it homeomorphic to the closed
wall there's also an infinite
dimensional version it turns out the
infinite dimensional
version of the same theorem of this fix
Point
theorem which is extremely useful in the
study of partial differential equation
do you know this abbreviation PD
is PD tend to be very difficult to study
but there's a topological geometric
approach to pdes very powerful and
extremely
simple in PDS
this version infinite dimensional
version of brow ruber is known as the
Sher fix Point
here sha was a Polish mathematician um
who died very young sha fix Point here
it's exactly the same idea but because
we haven't really prepared the
mathematics of infin dimensional spaces
I cannot mention it but it's really the
same idea as what we're discussing show
that
prove this theorem
in 1930 so 20 years after bu's original
theorem
okay let's prove this famous fixed Point
here we are proving that any continuous
map from a bolt itself must have a fixed
point now the first thing we notice is
that we have been studying the left shed
6.3m and that cannot be applied to this
situation immediately what hypothesis is
that
okay I cannot just say oh because of has
a fixed
point something is wrong in this context
what's the difficulty left sh applies to
what kind of
manifolds oriented oriented and closed
manifolds it cannot have boundaries but
this B has a boundary boundary is bad
for our intersection Theory because as
we saw as you deform the picture the
intersection might poof drop off the
boundary fall out of the boundary so we
have to somehow modify the
problem deform the problem in fact in
order to reduce it to a case when there
is no
boundary we cannot
apply left set directly
because unfortunately the boundary is
present boundary is not
empty so B is not
closed
okay so we have to resort to the trick
in order to translate this problem into
a problem with
B here's a trick so
please be patient with
us
regard B sub BM excuse me b super
M as the southern hemisphere I'll
explain what I
mean hemisphere of of the M dimensional
sphere m spere
s of
s okay and consider the following
picture here's the
[Applause]
picture please imagine this
sphere okay a
sphere surface of the Earth if you like
okay so that's a sphere imagine the
equator and imagine the path of the Sur
which is south of the Equator where we
live now southern hemisphere you get
this hemisphere which looks like a ball
you know the kind of salad bowl in which
aim s salad now this shape is
homeomorphic to a bow in this case a
disc do you agree if you get rid of the
Cur curvature and then just flatten it
on on the plane it just becomes a flat
disc so it is homomorphic to a dis
that's the case that's the sense in
which I say you should regard the ball
as the southern hemisphere of the sphere
of the same Dimension
so the
pictures can you see the pictures from
that distance in the corner I hope you
[Applause]
can this is um the sphere
s and what we are thinking about is that
this lower
half is
BM let's consider this map Pi which is
pi y Dela Pi because it's traditional in
Geometry pi as in
projection I'm just looking at the
sphere from above
and every Point goes straight down drops
down to thehere so points here somewhere
here will drop down to the point
straight underneath okay points on the
CN hemisphere don't
move okay so all the points on the
Northern Hemisphere and the equator St
drop down to the corresponding southern
hemisphere directly underneath points on
the sere don't move okay that's the m so
this is is what you call the vertical
projection once we're on the sun
hemisphere because we're regarding the
sere as B we can map it by f f is
mapping from the ball to the ball and
let's say that the here is a good way to
do it let's say this is the sere and
then its image let's say looks like
this by the way I drew it as has not
been subjective but it can be subjective
it can cover the entire ball that's fine
but it's contained inside the Southern
Hemisphere
okay and then
finally I'm going to put
another copy of SM and map it up what I
mean is I just put the sahem sphere as
the lower
Hemisphere okay so this is what is
called I
to be precise you see there's no dot it
is iot and it's the
inclusion okay in other words this is
mapped as a subset into into this so
it's not a stive map because no point on
the another hemisphere comes from this
map is that okay so every point on the
on this goes to the corresponding point
on the C Hemisphere and that's it all
right so we have those three Maps
vertical projection down F across and I
up finally and if you compose them you
get a map from SM to
SM
Now
by example 10 I told you this was not an
examp just an example but an important
one the if you compose this you get a
map from the sphere to sphere which is
not subjective the non
subjective composition
how do you compose first I Mark by pi
second I Mark by F and then third I
finish by mapping by
yot this composition is not subjective
why because no point here on the nor
hemisphere comes from any point there
you see all the points on the sphere
goes down to the hemisphere and I do
something on the Southern Hemisphere and
they just put theere up so it's not
subjective because the all the entire
Norther hemisphere is missed by the
image so this non subjective composition
is deformable by that example to a
constant
M okay and this composition goes from s
to
S now we are talking SM is closed
without boundary whereas the original
problem BM was not closed he had
boundary we can then apply
the the
theorem so SM is
closed or rather let's write it like
this the boundary of SM is empty so it's
a closed manifold so we can
apply the theorem 11 that we've just
approved we can apply the left shs
ideology left result and find the fixed
Point let's call it X of
the composition it's a fixed Point not
yet of f but it's a fixed point of the
composition in that it is x = i f pi x
like this is that
okay the theorem applies to this
composition which goes from SM to SM so
the fix point that we have found is not
yet the fix point for f that we want but
it's still the fix point of this
thing however we can almost we're almost
done let's call this formula
star the statement that X does not move
under the composition of those three
Maps but you see
let's discuss where this x can
be do you think X can be on the Northern
Hemisphere and not move after the
composition of those three
Maps can X this fix point be on the
Norther hemisphere no it can because
after this operation it drops down to
the Southern Hemisphere and then it goes
somewhere else on the Southern
Hemisphere by F and when I end up I end
up on the southern hemisphere so every
point on the Northern Hemisphere moves
to some point on the southern hemisphere
so this x cannot be on the Northern
Hemisphere this
composition Pi composed with f composed
with Yota
moves every
Point Northern
point
so X must be on the southern hemisphere
X must lie
on the southern
[Applause]
hemisphere but if x is on the sou
hemisphere what is the image of X by pi
what's pi of X huh it's exactly equal to
X it doesn't move under Pi because this
map just pushes all the nor hemisphere
on the Southern Hemisphere and leaves
the southern hemisphere alone so
then in this complicated looking formula
expression Pi of X is in fact
X yeah
and the
star simplifies
then and unfortunately I have to keep
going on that Blackboard I'm
sorry I want to make it fit better
simplifies to
xal
Yota F ofx because Pi of X is
X but what's y Yota is just putting the
southern hemisphere as part of northern
hemisphere
so Yota f ofx is exactly the same as f
ofx
yeah f ofx is somewhere here and in the
end I just put it as part of the larger
picture so it's exactly same thing and
miraculously you see we have found the
fixed
point for f which we
wanted fixed by F and of proof we have
found the fix point for the original map
from the ball to the ball you see what
we have done balll to the ball we cannot
use intersection Theory immediately
because ball has boundary but by
resorting to this trick I start a little
earlier from the sphere ston down and
then apply F and then fish up this trick
converts the problem into a problem
without boundary from sphere to sphere
and then we have to think a little hard
after I find a fix point for this
composition and a little bit of
thinking reveals that the fix point we
have found must have been a fix point of
the original
map okay that's what it
is
good I shall now finish um by issuing
one little warning and
tomorrow we'll see many many examples of
this theorem in action in applied
sciences please note that we
defined BM a long time ago to be the set
of all the points X1 through XM inside
RM such that the sum of the
squares is less than equal to one not
strictly less than one do you remember
in another words it contained the
bound you should realize that the
conclusion of the theorem we have just
proved the Brower fix Point theorem
conclusion brow fails so bra is not true
it's not a
theorem
if for the set that looks similar but
not the same the set of all the points
in our
M such that the sum of
squares is strictly one for this set
brow is
false you must be careful therefore when
you apply this kind of fix Point theorem
that either the manifold is closed then
you can apply defs or this ball or
something anything the ball have
contains all the boundary points then
you can apply brow but if you fail the
hypothesis then conclusion has no reason
be
true for example
instead of the closed ball in dimension
one let's consider the open ball on
Dimension One in other words minus one
to one this
interval without the end
points yes and consider the map X goes
to half of
X simple map take an X here and then map
it to half the X this map although it's
continuous and it seems to be mapping on
the ball acting on the ball on this in
interal I sorry this B Unit B has no
fixed
point now Nadia is going to complain
because this seems to have a fix Point
what's the fix point of this map zero ah
but n remembers
oh this is bad so I I'm sorry let's put
it like this I'm sorry about this so 0
to one so un need ah I'm sorry but okay
0 to one
this has a fixed point but this fixed
Point does not belong to the set so on
this set he has no fixed point and the
reason this fails is because this point
is this end is open if you close this
end and close this end and have any
continuous map from the this interal
itself then you have a fixed Point okay
so make sure when you apply Brower and
you have many occasions in the future to
apply browers F theum that the
hypothesis are
satisfied good